so I have a few questions from some
friends bande I've received a diagnosis of a
bande I've received a diagnosis of a
terminal illness
I understand that we all face mortality
but I now have a clearer timeline for my
own I've accepted this reality and feel
I've accepted this reality and feel
strong sense of urgency to deepen my
spiritual practice
it may be too late but I want to make
the most of my time that I have left
could you kindly suggest specific
contemplations or practices that I might
might Aid me on this journey
well it's the the practice doesn't
change you know whether you are where you have
you know whether you are where you have
a lot of time left a little one it's the
same gradual process it's the same
gradual training
so the gradual training we often talk
about well now that person will have to
condense it into much shorter period of
time so take the precepts very even more
seriously since restrained twice as hard
withdrawal from unwholesome States uh
exerting himself in complete seclusion
from others as well grasping the signs
of the mind it's it's always the same
pathway as the Buddha said when he
discovered a Dharma he was like an
ancient path that previous people people
in the past have walked but it's always
the same
it's not like you you can do different
things that approach them differently so
you just have to go through gradual
training just obviously more intensely
than uh than somebody who say is not
terminal ill it
it
reminds me of The Suitor
um
it says this is
because if five things do not slip away
from a frail and sick biku
you can't be expected of him in no long
time with the destruction of the tanks
he will realize for himself
The Liberation of mind
so these five things are a big who
dwells contemplating the
unattractiveness of the body perceiving
the repulsiveness of food
or the necessity of food
perceiving the non-delight in the entire
world contemplating a nature
and he has perception of death
well-established eternity give these
five things do not slip away from a
frail and sick dying
it will be expected that he will yeah uh
however the difference there is that die
in Baku is an area
he's not a putugina
he's already has a right view he just
hasn't completely reached the Liberation
and destruction of the things as it says
there so he would lead reach the destruction
so he would lead reach the destruction
of tense if he established himself in
those five things having had the right
view from beforehand
so I just presume that this person who
says my time is short now I haven't
practiced before as much now I have a
timeline I want to practice harder they
don't even have the right View
and for that again the gradual training
there is no shortcut there is just that
that long journey could be travel faster
if you double down with your efforts if
you increase the amount double them up
then um take it seriously not looking at
um take it seriously not looking at
anything unwholesome not thinking about
anything unwholesome withdrawing
yourself exerting yourself in seclusion
in secluded places for as long as you
can grasping the signs of the mind like
listen to the talks about the signs of
the mind and so on because that's a
precursor to the right View
um and sure you can in the contemplate
all this contemplate the illness and
impulsiveness but that applies that can
result in The Liberation from from
destruction of detains if you know what
the practice is if you have the right
view then that would amplify it
so an ordinary person that's now facing
death obviously afraid
he's like oh
I should have I haven't been practicing
well yeah then that's the thing really
um everybody's facing death
and that terminal ill person he might
actually live longer than somebody else
who's not terminal ill
so it's really just uh just the the
recognition of the inevitable in their
case but yeah sometimes that's what people
but yeah sometimes that's what people
some people need or I think most people
will probably need something like that
to to make them really take the practice
seriously seriously yeah
but there is no special contemplation
that can then
provide a shortcut for you it's still
the same path you have to walk the same
distance but yes you can walk it faster
if you take the the steps of the gradual
training more seriously
you're seeing the danger in the
slightest fault moderating eating all of
that is building up building up building
up intensifying amplifying
and uh and it said like then when you
know when that
seeking secluded places when you're
dwelling in physical seclusion it says
that's a prerequisite for grasping the
signs of the Mind
so because that somebody can grasp the
signs of the mind having not been
physically secluded that's not possible
it's impossible
so if you do have physical seclusion and
have been practicing sensory stream
virtue everything leading up to it and
you're able to sort of
um endure it rightly it's it's quite
possible you will grasp the signs of
your mind you will start seeing your own
mind as a phenomenon as an entity that exists
as a phenomenon as an entity that exists
here parallel to this body existing
neither of which really belongs to you
you will you will be able to see it in a
correct third person sense so to speak
like a wild animal that needs taming
you will be able to unidentify yourself
with it by default which is what's
usually done
you're identified by default
you don't even see the mind you don't
even see there's a thing you might have
a concept ideas of it but you don't see
it you don't see it as a phenomenon
existing there while you're thinking
about it
and for that in order to see it you you
you you need to develop that gradual
training Solitude and then these things
can become more apparent so that would
be my advice really strive for that
before time Runs Out
and and actually do yeah do things that
are that lead to peace which is the
greatest training but you know you
sometimes I I've heard advice like you
you reflect on the
be grateful for the things that have
happened in your life and think about
all the good things and you know it's
more about having a how to have a
peaceful death that's not a peaceful
death uh that's the the idea of the peaceful
uh that's the the idea of the peaceful
death usually comes from people that
don't contemplate death correctly they
are still intoxicated with life and then
they project this fantasy of dying
peacefully peaceful uh from the point of
view of an external Observer what looks
peaceful um the only peaceful death is the death
um the only peaceful death is the death
of another hunt
because that's the only
state of the five Aggregates that has
been freed from any traces of resistance
of patiga if there is still resistance
there is patiga there will be uh there
will be some tension felt when death
occurs because it's not completely
because it's not completely
dispassionate so you want to be want to
experience peaceful death you need to
become another hunt you want to
experience uh
uh
less unpeaceful death will become at
least a sodepana
but that's really the measure of the
piece not how you look externally
sometimes people look externally
peaceful just because they've been wiped
wiped Away by their illness and there's
absolutely no energy or strength left
so it just looks peaceful
but internally the only peaceful State
of Mind is the mind that has been
developed in this passion
disenchantment then there will be no
resistance to death
and that's pretty much what I'm
describing develop the sign of the Mind
get the right View and you're already
step closer to being unmoved by Death
if in your spare time when I practice
gratitude and what not
visualize your whatever happy lofty
ideas and so on yeah do that but don't
conflate that with the practice of the
Right View and gradual training because
there's nothing to do with it
it's more like just making yourself feel
better because you still don't know the
Escape but why don't you start seeking the
but why don't you start seeking the
escape by admitting that you don't know
the Escape
you don't have to make yourself feel
better you can but don't again don't confuse
you can but don't again don't confuse
that for the practice
and if your concern is about making
yourself feel better
you won't be then practicing towards the
Right View because practicing towards
Right View probably won't make you feel
better initially it is going to make you
feel worse
because you're uncovering things so they
become mutually they don't need to be
mutually exclusive but practically
they're mutually exclusive for somebody
who is at that stage
you would not be able to make yourself
feel better and practice for the Right
View if the value of feeling good is
still more important to you
so
but I think this person has realized
that because
having being diagnosed with a terminal
illness they are asking the right things
what they do to speed up what I haven't
done before